<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall, May the seventh, MDCLXXVI by John Svdbvry ...</title>
            <author>Sudbury, John, 1604-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61951</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6138</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R624</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11944930</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11944930</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51305</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61951)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51305)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 516:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall, May the seventh, MDCLXXVI by John Svdbvry ...</title>
                  <author>Sudbury, John, 1604-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Newcomb, and are to be sold by John Herringman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] In the Savoy :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 1st, III, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51305:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON <hi>PREACHED</hi> before the KING AT White-Hall, <hi>MAY</hi> the Seventh, MDCLXXVI.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>JOHN S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY,</hi> D.D. And DEAN of <hi>Durham,</hi> Chaplain in Ordinary to His MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties ſpecial Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>SAVOY:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Newcomb;</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>John Herringman</hi> next to the Fountain-Tavern in the <hi>Strand.</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:51305:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51305:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 TIM. 3.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—The Pillar and Ground of the Truth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE care of all the Churches, which lay upon St. <hi>Paul,</hi> would neither ſuffer him to keep a conſtant reſidence upon any one of them, nor to leave them as Sheep without a Shepherd to have that care of them in his abſence, which he himſelf had when he was preſent with them.</p>
            <p>And therefore having ſpent ſome time at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> he departed from thence into <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia,</hi> leaving the care of that Church to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy;</hi> and wrote this Epiſtle to him, to let him know how he ought to behave himſelf in ſo excellent and worthy a Province as that was, which he had committed to him, as he tells him in this and the former Verſe: <hi>Theſe things write I unto thee, hoping to come unto thee ſhortly. But if I tarry long, that thou mayſt know how thou oughteſt to behave thy ſelf in the Houſe of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51305:3"/>God, which is the Church of the living God, the Pillar and Ground of the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words he ſets before him the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of that Church, which he had committed to his care, in three excellent Titles; <hi>The Houſe of God; The Church of the living God; The Pillar and Ground of the Truth:</hi> Every one of which, is very worthy of a diſtinct and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Conſideration; but this laſt hath the moſt need of it, becauſe it hath been very much perplex'd with a great deal of work about it, to make it ſerve the pride and ambition of a Church, of which there is not ſo much as any mention throughout the whole Epiſtle. All the Greatneſs of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty of Power and Juriſdiction which it claims over all other Churches, the Infallibility of all her Doctrines, and an Immoveable Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Truth, from which it can never fall, are charged upon this Text; but how unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, we ſhall ſee in the Examination of theſe three Particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. The <hi>Church,</hi> which is here called <hi>The Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and Ground of the Truth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. The <hi>Truth</hi> of which <hi>this</hi> Church is <hi>The Pillar and Ground.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51305:3"/>
               <item>III. The importance of theſe words, <hi>The Pillar and Ground of the Truth.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Where it will not be <hi>hard</hi> to make it <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>evident,</hi> that this pretended infallible Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Truth, is very much miſtaken in every one of theſe Particulars; <hi>The Church; The Truth;</hi> and, <hi>The Pillar and Ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Church,</hi> of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in theſe words, was not the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The <hi>Truth</hi> of which he ſpeaks, was not the <hi>Truth</hi> of which the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> takes upon it to be the <hi>Pillar and Ground.</hi> The <hi>Pillar and Ground</hi> in <hi>their</hi> ſenſe is not the ſenſe of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> and in the ſenſe of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> there was not any <hi>Church</hi> in the World to which this Honour of being <hi>the Pillar and Ground of the Truth,</hi> was not more due than it is to the preſent Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, for the Church, nothing can be more <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>evident,</hi> than that the <hi>Church</hi> of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in <hi>theſe</hi> words, was not the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus:</hi> for <hi>Timothy,</hi> to whom he wrote this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, was not the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> There St. <hi>Paul</hi> left him, when he depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from thence into <hi>Macedonia;</hi> and he left
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51305:4"/>him to <hi>abide there,</hi> and to do the Office of a Biſhop <hi>there,</hi> as he tells him at the <hi>beginning</hi> of this <hi>Epiſtle. I beſought thee to abide ſtill at</hi> Epheſus, <hi>when I went into</hi> Macedonia, <hi>that thou mighteſt charge ſome that they teach no other Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Epheſus</hi> is called the <hi>Pillar and Ground of the Truth,</hi> not as it was the <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Church</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> divided from all <hi>other</hi> Churches, as the City of <hi>Epheſus</hi> was divided from all other Cities: Nor as the Viſible Head of them all: But as it was one with them all in the Communion of that one <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> Church, of which that and all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches were ſo many Parts and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Which <hi>one Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> Church, was <hi>One,</hi> not by a corporal aſſembling together in one place, but by an <hi>unanimous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> of one and the ſame <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick</hi> Faith and Doctrine, and Diſcipline, which was of more Power and Vertue to make them all <hi>one,</hi> than any diſtance of place, or difference of <hi>Laws, Languages, Cuſtoms, Manners,</hi> or any other difference among them, could be to make them <hi>two.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Catholick,</hi> becauſe it was not limited to any Nation, as the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> was confin'd to one Family,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51305:4"/>which was the Houſe of <hi>Jacob;</hi> and all their Sacrifices to one place, which was the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> but extended to all men every where, without any diſtinction of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, Barbarians, Scythians,</hi> bond and free, male and female. Thirdly, <hi>Apoſtolick,</hi> becauſe that one <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith and Doctrine in which they were all join'd together in one, was that which they all had received from the <hi>Apoſtles, whoſe ſound was gone out into all the Earth,
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.18.</note> and their words unto the ends of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as that one <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick Church</hi> was the <hi>Pillar and Ground of the Truth,</hi> by their viſible profeſſion of that Truth, as we ſhall ſee afterwards: So particular Churches, which made a viſible profeſſion of the ſame <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick Truth,</hi> were one with it, and every one of them might be call'd a <hi>Pillar and Ground of the Truth,</hi> eſpecially ſuch of them as were the moſt <hi>eminent</hi> and <hi>conſpicuous;</hi> and ſuch was the <hi>Church of Epheſus.</hi> For as the Churches of the <hi>East</hi> were more numerous and conſpicuous when St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote this <hi>Epistle,</hi> than the Churches of the <hi>Weſt:</hi> ſo the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> was of great note and eminence among the <hi>Churches</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt.</hi> It was as emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent a <hi>Church</hi> for the profeſſion of the Truth of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51305:5"/>Chriſtian Religion, as the City of <hi>Epheſus</hi> was for Heatheniſh <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Superſtition,</hi> when it was a Worſhipper of the great <hi>Goddeſs Diana,</hi> and of the Image which fell down from <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> The Preaching of the Goſpel had ſuch an influence from that City,
<note place="margin">Act. 19.10.</note> which was the <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis</hi> of the leſſer <hi>Aſia,</hi> that <hi>all they which dwelt in</hi> Aſia <hi>heard the word of the Lord Jeſus, both Jews and Greeks.</hi> The Men of Learning, who had buſied their Wits, and ſpent much of their time in the ſtudy of Curious Arts, were ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with it, as not only to renounce all further ſtudy of thoſe Curious Arts; but to ſhew their reſolution never to return to that Study again, <hi>they brought their Books together and burned them before all men;
<note place="margin">Act. 19.19, 20.</note> and they counted the price of them; and found it fifty thouſand pieces of ſilver: ſo mightily grew the Word of God, and prevailed.</hi> And the Crafts-men of the City, who got their Wealth by making Silver Shrines for <hi>Diana,</hi> were ſo alarm'd at the ſucceſs of it, as to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that <hi>the Temple of the great Goddeſs</hi> Diana <hi>would be deſpis'd, and her Magnificence deſtroyed, whom all</hi> Aſia <hi>and the World worſhipped.</hi> And which troubled them more, their Trade was in great danger to be loſt; for that was the firſt Argument which <hi>Demetrius</hi> us'd to raiſe them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51305:5"/>up into an uproar, Verſ. 25. <hi>Sirs, ye know that by this Craft we have our Wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> had this further Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, not only to be one of the <hi>Seven Churches</hi> which were preſented to St. <hi>John,</hi> in the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Seven Golden Candleſticks, and Chriſt in the midſt of them, commanding him to write ſo many <hi>Epiſtles</hi> to them, which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf dictated to him; but to be the <hi>firſt of them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 1.11.</note> and the Character which he gives of that Church, is ſuch as might well become a <hi>Church</hi> which was a <hi>Pillar and Ground of the Truth:
<note place="margin">Revel. 2.2, 3.</note> I know thy works, and thy labour, and thy pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and how thou canſt not bear them which are evil: And thou haſt tryed them which ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not, and hast found them lyars; and haſt born, and haſt patience, and for my Names ſake haſt laboured, and haſt not fainted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> which had all this Honour, had aſpir'd to a Supremacy over <hi>all other Churches,</hi> it might have made a fairer Title to it by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> than that which the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> hath made by St. <hi>Peter.</hi> For St.
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> was <hi>ſeparated to his Office from his Mothers Womb.</hi> He was called to it in a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and extraordinary manner, by <hi>Christ</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51305:6"/>to him in a Viſion <hi>from Heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 9.3.</note> He was honour'd by him with this Character,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note> 
               <hi>He is a choſen Veſſel unto me, to bear my Name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Gentiles and Kings, and the Children of Iſrael.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.5.</note> He was not a whit behind the very chief Apoſtles.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.10</note> He laboured more abundantly than they all.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.28.</note> The care of all the Churches lay upon him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15.20.</note> He <hi>ſtrived to preach the Goſpel not where Christ was named, leſt he ſhould build up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another mans foundation. He conferred not with fleſh and blood,
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.16, 17</note> neither went he up to</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem <hi>to them that were Apoſtles before him. They who ſeem'd to be ſomewhat in conference added nothing to him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.6.</note> He was ſo far from learning any thing of St.
<note place="margin">Verſ. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Peter,</hi> and from look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon him as his Superiour, that <hi>he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood him to the face;</hi> and told him plainly, that he, and others whom he had miſled, <hi>walked not uprightly according to the truth of the Goſpel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> And St. <hi>Peter</hi> was ſo far from rebuking him for his inſolence, as to make an honourable mention of him:
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>Our beloved Brother</hi> Paul, <hi>according to the Wiſdom given to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who was thus highly honour'd, had been Preaching the Goſpel to the <hi>Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> for the ſpace of <hi>three years:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 20.31.</note> But there is not ſo much as any expreſs mention in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51305:6"/>Scripture that ever St. <hi>Peter</hi> was at <hi>Rome;</hi> and we may ſee they are hard put to prove it, when they cannot alledge any one Text for it but that,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>The Church which is at</hi> Babylon <hi>elect to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with you, ſaluteth you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was likewiſe a ſingular care which St. <hi>Paul</hi> had of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> that in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence he commended the care of it to <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.1.</note> a perſon indear'd to him by many Names;
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.1. Col. 1.1. Rom. 16.21.</note> His <hi>own Son in the Faith;</hi> His <hi>beloved Son;</hi> His <hi>Brother;</hi> His <hi>Work-fellow:</hi> and wrote two Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to him, to let him know how he ought to behave himſelf in ſo excellent and worthy a Province as that which he calleth <hi>The Houſe of God, the Church of the living God, the Pillar and Ground of the Truth.</hi> Whereas St. <hi>Peter</hi> never wrote any one Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> nor do we read of any one whom he left to take care of that Church in his abſence, though he was ſo much abſent that it is much doubted whether he were ever there.</p>
            <p>For all that the ancient Fathers have written of his being Biſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi> ſeven years, and after that Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> twenty and five years, and after that crucified under <hi>Nero,</hi> is upon the Teſtimony of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> of whom <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith that he was deceiv'd in ſome things, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51305:7"/>we are very well aſſur'd that he was deceived in this: for three years after St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Converſion, he went up, not to <hi>Rome,</hi> but <hi>to Jeruſalem,</hi> to ſee <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal 1.18.</note> and there he found him, <hi>and abode with him fifteen days.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.1, 9.</note> Then <hi>fourteen years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he went up again to Jeruſalem;</hi> and there he found him. He was preſent at the Council at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as we read <hi>Act.</hi> 15. which was eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years after Chriſt: And in the former Chapters of the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> we find him there, or thereabouts, a great way from <hi>Rome.</hi> After that he preach'd the Goſpel to thoſe of <hi>Pontus, Aſia, Galatia, Cappadocia,</hi> and <hi>Bithynia.</hi> And if after all this time he ſate Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi> ſeven years, and after that five and twenty years Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> he muſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live <hi>Nero</hi> more years than <hi>Nero</hi> Reigned, and therefore he could not be crucified under him.</p>
            <p>But as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who knew very well that he <hi>was not a whit behind the very chief Apoſtles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.5.</note> did never offer to put himſelf before and above them all; and among the Apoſtles there were ſome who in regard of their Perſonal Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are called <hi>Chief and Pillars,</hi> yet without any Juriſdiction over the reſt: ſo among Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, though the Churches of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> were more numerous, and of greater note than thoſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51305:7"/>of the <hi>Weſt,</hi> they never requir'd any ſubjection from them; and among the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches, though the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> was of great note and eminence, it never aſſumed any Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty over the other Churches. There is no ground in Scripture, nor in the Catholick and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, that will afford any ſtanding for ſuch a Pillar, as that of a Local Church, which is to all other Churches as the <hi>Head</hi> in a Body to all the Members of that Body, as a <hi>Foundation</hi> in a Building to all the Building that ſtands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, as a <hi>Root</hi> in a Tree to all the Branches: For though the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> arrogates to it ſelf all theſe Titles, together with that of the <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick Church,</hi> this is ſo far from being <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick Truth,</hi> that it is neither <hi>Catholick,</hi> nor <hi>Apoſtolick,</hi> nor <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It is not Catholick: for though the City of <hi>Rome</hi> had that Dominion over the Kings of the Earth, for which it was called <hi>Caput Orbis,</hi> the Head of the World; the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> did never claim any ſuch Headſhip over all other Churches for above three hundred years after St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote this Epiſtle: and was ſo far from denying her Communion to all other Churches, but thoſe which would accept it upon ſuch
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51305:8"/>terms as thoſe, which <hi>Nahaſh</hi> the <hi>Ammonite</hi> propos'd to the men of <hi>Jabeſh-Gilead;
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 11.2.</note> On this condition will I make a Covenant with you, that I may thruſt out all your right eyes.</hi> Or from ſaying to them as the Bramble in the Parable of <hi>Jotham</hi> ſaid unto the Trees;
<note place="margin">Judg. 9.15.</note> 
               <hi>If in truth ye anoint me King over you, then come, and put your truſt in my ſhadow: and if not, let fire come out of the Bramble, and devour the Cedars of</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon. That in the ſixth Canon of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Nice,</hi> which in the <hi>Arabick</hi> Canons is the eighth, the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is propoſed as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> to contain himſelf within his own limits.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is not Apoſtolick; for the Apoſtles knew nothing of any <hi>Superiority</hi> and <hi>Subjection</hi> among themſelves, or among the <hi>Churches</hi> which were founded by them. They knew no other Head of the Church,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.18.</note> but Him, <hi>who is the beginning, the first-born from the dead, that in all things he might have the pre-eminence.</hi> They knew no other Foundation, but that of <hi>Apoſtles and Prophets;
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.20.</note> Jeſus Chriſt himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the chief corner-ſtone.</hi> And in that Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion all the Apoſtles were as much of the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation as any one of them, and therefore are called <hi>Twelve Foundations,</hi> Revel. 21.14.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51305:8"/>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was in ſome ſenſe the Root of all Churches; St. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it ſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17. But it never claimed any Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority over all other Churches upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. But as for the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> he ſaith plainly in the ſame Verſe, that it was not the Root, but a Branch of a Wild-Olive graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed in among other Branches, and with them partook of the Root and Fatneſs of the Olive-Tree. And as if he had foreſeen how ready that Church would be to boaſt it ſelf againſt other Churches, he gives them an Admonition againſt it, in the next Verſe: <hi>Boaſt not againſt the Branches: but if thou boaſt, thou beareſt not the Root, but the Root thee.</hi> And argues the matter with them in the next Verſe: <hi>Thou wilt ſay then, the Branches were broken off, that I might be graffed in. Well, becauſe of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief they were broken off, and thou ſtandeſt by Faith: be not high-minded, but fear; for if God ſpared not the Natural Branches, take heed leſt he alſo ſpare not thee.</hi> And ſets before them the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Gods Severity againſt the Natural Branches, as a warning to them not to be high-minded, but fear, at the next Verſe: <hi>Behold therefore the Goodneſs and Severity of God: on them which fell, Severity; but towards thee,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51305:9"/>Goodneſs, if thou continue in his Goodneſs, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thou alſo ſhalt be cut off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. As it is not <hi>Catholick</hi> nor <hi>Apoſtolick,</hi> ſo it is ſo far from <hi>Truth,</hi> that there never was a more Fundamental Errour, than that of a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Church, which is ſuch a <hi>Pillar and Ground of Truth,</hi> that it cannot err. But if in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> there is no mention of ſuch a <hi>Pillar and Ground of Truth;</hi> and in this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> where theſe words are found, there is not any mention of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I need not ſay any more to ſhew how much they are out in the firſt Particular, which is the <hi>Church.</hi> Let us proceed to the ſecond Particular, which is the <hi>Truth;</hi> and ſee if they be not as much out in the <hi>Truth,</hi> as they are in the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Truth</hi> of which the Church is the <hi>Pillar and Ground,</hi> is not <hi>all</hi> Truth: For there are <hi>many</hi> Truths for which the Church is <hi>not</hi> concern'd; they may ſtand or fall according to the ſtrength or weakneſs of thoſe Arguments by which they are ſupported, or with which they are aſſaulted, without any peril or preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to the <hi>Church.</hi> God who would have all men to be ſaved, and to come to the knowledge of the Truth, hath ſet up a <hi>Church</hi> to lead men
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51305:9"/>to the knowledge of all that <hi>Truth</hi> which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for them, that they may be ſaved: but as for many other Truths, which are profeſs'd and taught in Schools and Univerſities; as all men are not born to be bred up in them, ſo the knowledge of them is not ſo neceſſary to them, but that they may be ſaved without it. When Chriſt promis'd his Diſciples that he would ſend them <hi>the Spirit of Truth,
<note place="margin">Joh. 16.13.</note> to guide them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Truth,</hi> He ſpake of that Truth which was neceſſary for them to know, for the diſcharging of that Office and Miniſtry which he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them, not all other Truth. And therefore when the <hi>Manichees</hi> gloried in him who was the Patriarch of their Sect, that he was a man full of the Holy Ghoſt, and led in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Truth, for that he could diſcourſe of Truths in Aſtronomy, and other Mathematical Sciences; St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> anſwer'd them very well, That this was no Argument to prove that he was full of the Holy Ghoſt: for the Holy Ghoſt was not given to lead men into ſuch Truths; for he was not given to make Mathematicians, but Chriſtians. And though it is true that the <hi>Infallible Chair</hi> doth not in theſe days meddle with Truths of this nature, there was a time when it did; but ſo unluckily, as to condemn
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51305:10"/>one <hi>Virgilius</hi> for holding that there were <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podes,</hi> and that the Earth is round, and the Sun, and Moon, and Stars, move about it in the other Hemiſphere, as they do in this; which is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrable Truth.</p>
            <p>But to let this paſs, as it is not all Truth, ſo neither is it all Theological Truth, or Truth in Divinity: for Divinity is a Science, in which there are ſome Truths which dwell in that Light which is ſo inacceſſible, that the moſt learned men are not aſham'd to confeſs that ſuch know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is too wonderful for them, and that they cannot attain unto it. And there be many other Truths about which learned men may differ in opinion, and diſpute with ſo much probability on either ſide, that though the Truth cannot be with both of them, becauſe what the one affirms, the other denieth; yet they who are in the Errour may be perſwaded that the Truth is with them, and their Errour ſhall not prejudice their Salvation, unleſs they ſuffer themſelves to be led into it by ſome prejudice or paſſion, or be ſo obſtinate in it as to ſhew that they ſeek not Truth, but Victory; and would rather per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in an Errour, than by ſuffering themſelves to be led out of it, ſeem to acknowledge that they were in an Errour. The Scriptures, which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51305:10"/>are able to make all men wiſe unto Salvation, are not ſo clear and evident in all things, but that we may ſay of other Books of Scripture, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith of the Epiſtles of St. <hi>Paul, There are ſome things in them hard to be underſtood:</hi> But the more hard they are to be underſtood, the leſs neceſſary they are to be known. God, who hath made the Fruits of the Earth, which are neceſſary for the food and ſuſtenance of men, to grow upon the face of it, where every eye may ſee them, and every hand may gather them; but hid the Mines of Gold and Silver, which ſerve for Riches and Ornament, in the Bowels of the Earth, where they cannot be found but with much ſeeking, nor be wrought out, and purged from that Droſs with which they are mixt, but with great labour, hath likewiſe made all that Truth which is neceſſary to feed the Souls of men to Eternal Life, ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be found, that we may ſay of that, as the <hi>Wiſe-man</hi> ſaith of Wiſdom,
<note place="margin">Wiſd. 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>Wiſdom is eaſily ſeen of them that love her, and found of ſuch as ſeek her.</hi> But there be many other Truths which ſerve to inrich and adorn the Soul, which he hath reſerv'd to exerciſe and reward the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and ſtudy of them that <hi>ſeek for them as for Silver, and as for hidden Treaſures.</hi> If there
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51305:11"/>were an Infallible Oracle to determine all Truths, the eaſineſs of coming to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them would much abate and leſſen the value and eſteem of them: but when the difficulty of finding them excites deſire, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſtirs up labour and ſtudy, and labour and ſtudy find that Truth which could not be found without it, it is the more joyfully embrac'd, and more ſtedfaſtly retain'd.</p>
            <p>But, Thirdly, The Truth of which the <hi>Church</hi> is the <hi>Pillar</hi> and <hi>Ground,</hi> is <hi>that Truth</hi> which is no where to be found but in the <hi>Church;</hi> but is ſo manifeſt in the profeſſion of the Church, that they who cannot find it any where elſe, may find it there. For as in all Sciences there are ſome <hi>Truths</hi> which are <hi>proper</hi> and <hi>peculiar</hi> to them, as Truths in Logick, Truths in Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Moral Philoſophy, Truths in all Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Sciences: ſo there are ſome Truths in Divinity which are proper and peculiar to it, which as they could never have been known but by Divine Revelation, ſo they have been made known to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> by the Spirit of Truth, which was given to them to guide them into all Truth, and by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to the <hi>Church.</hi> Such is that which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth, <hi>The Truth of the Goſpel,</hi> Col. 1.5. <hi>The Truth of Chriſt,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51305:11"/>2 Cor. 11.10. <hi>The Truth of God,</hi> Rom. 15.8. And many times it is called <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>the Truth,</hi> without any note of difference from all other <hi>Truth. Truth,</hi> in oppoſition to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the <hi>Heathen</hi> as <hi>Truth,</hi> is oppos'd to Falſhood and Lyes: <hi>Truth,</hi> in oppoſition to the Religion of the <hi>Jews</hi> as Truth, is oppos'd to Figures and Shadows: <hi>Truth,</hi> in oppoſition to all <hi>other</hi> Truth, not as contrary to it; for one Truth cannot be contrary to another, but in a ſuperlative ſenſe the moſt excellent and moſt incomparable Truth. For though all <hi>Truth</hi> is <hi>Truth,</hi> yet as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the Law and the Goſpel compar'd together,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>Even that which was made glorious had no glory by reaſon of the glory that excelleth:</hi> So we may ſay of Truths in Philoſophy and all Sciences, compar'd with the Truth of the Goſpel, That which is Truth is not Truth in compariſon of the Truth that excelleth. Such is the Truth of which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaks in the next words to theſe of the Text, which ſome have joyn'd together, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding theſe words by them: <hi>Without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie great is the Myſtery of Godlineſs: God was manifeſt in the Fleſh, justified in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſeen of Angels, preached unto the Gentiles, believed on in the World, received in Glory.</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:51305:12"/>The <hi>Truth</hi> which he calleth the <hi>Truth which is after Godlineſs in hope of Eternal Life, which God that cannot lye promiſed before the World began, but hath in due time manifeſted his Word through Preaching.</hi> The <hi>Truth</hi> by which we are begotten again, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Of his own Will begat he us again by the Word of Truth</hi> The <hi>Truth</hi> that maketh us Free-men, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.32. <hi>Ye ſhall know the Truth, and the Truth ſhall make you free.</hi> The ſanctifying <hi>Truth, Joh.</hi> 17.17. <hi>Sanctifie them with thy Truth, thy Word is Truth.</hi> The ſaving <hi>Truth,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. <hi>God would have all men to be ſaved, and to come to the knowledge of the Truth.</hi> And this is the <hi>Truth</hi> of which the Church is the <hi>Pillar and Ground</hi> in the ſenſe of St. <hi>Paul.</hi> Now what ſenſe that is, follows in my third and laſt Particular, which is the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of theſe words, <hi>The Pillar and Ground of the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are two words, the <hi>Pillar</hi> and <hi>Ground,</hi> but they are very well joyn'd together, for they ſignifie two things which are joyn'd together in a Pillar that ſtandeth firm and ſtedfaſt. The former word ſignifieth that which we call the <hi>Body</hi> of the Pillar; the latter word ſignifieth the <hi>Baſis,</hi> or <hi>Foundation,</hi> or <hi>Foot</hi> of the Pillar: both together fignifie a Pillar ſtanding upon a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51305:12"/>Baſis or Foundation. But the <hi>Pillar and Ground of Truth,</hi> is a <hi>Metaphorical</hi> Expreſſion, and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphors</hi> are apt to beget <hi>Miſtakes:</hi> for in every <hi>Metaphor</hi> there is ſomething which is <hi>like,</hi> and ſomething which is <hi>not like;</hi> and as when the Metaphor is taken from ſomething wherein there is a <hi>likeneſs,</hi> the Metaphorical Expreſſion makes the ſenſe more <hi>elegant</hi> and clear; but when it is <hi>ſtretched</hi> to ſomething wherein there is <hi>no likeneſs,</hi> in ſtead of making the ſenſe <hi>more clear,</hi> it makes <hi>non-ſenſe.</hi> As in this Metaphor of <hi>the Pillar and Ground of Truth:</hi> A Pillar, or rather <hi>many</hi> Pillars, upon which a Houſe or Church is built, (as the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was built upon many <hi>Pillars,</hi> and ſo was the Temple of <hi>Diana</hi> at <hi>Epheſus</hi>) the Pillars are as the <hi>Foundation</hi> upon which the Houſe or <hi>Church</hi> is built, as the <hi>Foot</hi> of the Pillar is to the Pillar which ſtands upon it. But in this ſenſe neither the <hi>Church of Epheſus,</hi> nor the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> nor any <hi>National Church,</hi> nor the whole <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick Church,</hi> could be well and truly called <hi>The Pillar and Ground of Truth;</hi> becauſe the <hi>Truth</hi> is not built upon the <hi>Church,</hi> but the <hi>Church</hi> upon the <hi>Truth.</hi> And as there could never have been a <hi>True Church,</hi> if the <hi>Truth of the Church</hi> had not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51305:13"/>been <hi>before</hi> the <hi>Church:</hi> ſo if the <hi>Truth</hi> be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from the <hi>Church,</hi> it is no longer a True Church. There is no Power or Authority in <hi>any Church,</hi> to make any thing a <hi>Truth</hi> which was not a <hi>Truth before.</hi> The Apoſtles delivered the <hi>whole</hi> Faith to the Church; and if all the Churches in the World ſhould joyn together, they cannot make <hi>one new</hi> Article of Faith: All that they can do, is to <hi>deliver</hi> what they have <hi>receiv'd</hi> from them who have delivered what <hi>they alſo received,</hi> till we come at laſt to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who delivered what <hi>they</hi> alſo receiv'd from the <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> by which they were led into all that <hi>Truth,</hi> which could not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be made known to them, and aſſiſted in delivering thoſe <hi>Truths</hi> which were by other <hi>infallible</hi> proofs made known to them.</p>
            <p>But beſide thoſe many Pillars upon which Houſes and Churches were built, there were <hi>ſingle</hi> Pillars erected by the <hi>Heathen,</hi> to ſuch purpoſes, as do ſerve very well to expreſs the ſenſe of <hi>this</hi> Metaphor, which the Apoſtle here uſeth by way of <hi>alluſion</hi> to them.</p>
            <p>As firſt, There were Pillars which they rear'd up on high with Images of their <hi>Gods and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſes</hi> upon them, ſitting or ſtanding, or in ſome other poſture to attract the <hi>eyes</hi> of men to look
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51305:13"/>up to them with that <hi>Reſpect</hi> and <hi>Veneration</hi> which is due to <hi>Divine</hi> things. Of ſuch Pillars we read <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.1. <hi>Ye ſhall make you no Idols, nor Graven Image, neither rear you up a ſtanding Image or Pillar,</hi> as it is in the <hi>Margin.</hi> Now as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Heathen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.25.</note> that they <hi>changed the Truth of God into a Lye;</hi> and the Prophet <hi>Habakkuk</hi> calleth an Idol a <hi>Teacher of Lyes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. 2.18.</note> So we may ſay of thoſe Pillars of Idols, they were Pillars of <hi>Lyes.</hi> And in alluſion to them the <hi>Church,</hi> which ſets up the <hi>true</hi> Worſhip of the <hi>true</hi> God, above all the <hi>falſe</hi> Worſhip of all <hi>falſe</hi> gods, to draw the eyes of all men to look up to it with that <hi>Veneration</hi> which is due to it, may be called the Pillar and Ground of Truth, <hi>Excelſa Columna,</hi> according to that which the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> foretold of it in another Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 2.2. <hi>It ſhall come to paſs in the laſt days, that the Mountain of the Lords Houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the top of the Mountains, and ſhall be exalted above the Hills; and all Nations ſhall flow unto it.</hi> But in this ſenſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is more like to thoſe <hi>Pillars</hi> of the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi> than any other Chriſtian Church. For though it doth not ſet up thoſe <hi>Idols</hi> and <hi>Images</hi> of the <hi>Heathen</hi> to be worſhipped; it ſets up <hi>Images</hi> and <hi>Creatures</hi> to be worſhipped, which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51305:14"/>are either <hi>made</hi> Idols, or are in ſo much <hi>danger</hi> to be made <hi>Idols,</hi> that by the Confeſſion of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> they that worſhip God in an Image, or in a Creature, expoſe themſelves to great peril, and are forced to uſe the moſt ſubtil di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, which <hi>learned</hi> men do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, much leſs the <hi>ignorant and unlearned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, We read of many <hi>Pillars</hi> erected by the <hi>Heathen,</hi> with <hi>Inſcriptions</hi> upon them; Inſcriptions of <hi>Historical</hi> Narrations, of which it may be ſome were <hi>true,</hi> and ſome were <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous;</hi> and many other Inſcriptions of <hi>Laws, Leagues, Covenants, Precepts, Decrees, My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, &amp;c.</hi> in which ſenſe the Metaphor of a Pillar is uſed, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Him that overcometh will I make a Pillar in the Temple of my God—and I will write upon him the Name of my God, and the Name of the City of my God, which is the New Jeruſalem which cometh down out of Heaven from my God; and I will write upon him my new Name.</hi> In this ſenſe the <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick Church</hi> which expoſeth the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, which <hi>Ireneus</hi> calleth the <hi>Pillar</hi> and <hi>Ground</hi> of the Faith of the Church, and in which are written the <hi>Oracles of God,</hi> his <hi>Laws, Covenants, Decrees, Myſteries</hi> of his Will, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of his <hi>Providence,</hi> and many other <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51305:14"/>Truths,</hi> to be as legible as <hi>Inſcriptions</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Pillar; and every particular Church, which makes a viſible profeſſion of all that Truth which it hath receiv'd from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the whole <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> Church, ſo far forth as it is one with that <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick</hi> Church, is a Pillar and Ground of the Truth, <hi>Inſcripta Columna,</hi> a Pillar bearing thoſe <hi>Inſcriptions</hi> upon it, in ſuch Characters as make them legible to all men. But in this ſenſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> cannot ſo well be called a <hi>Pillar</hi> and <hi>Ground</hi> of the Truth, as other Churches.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe other Churches, <hi>Hebrew, Greek, Perſian, Syrian, Arabian, Ethiopian,</hi> have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd the Scriptures to be read in their Vulgar Tongue: But the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> doth not expoſe the Scriptures to be read but in a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage which the greateſt part of them that are concern'd to know the Truths which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd in them, do not underſtand; by which means they have kept the people in ſo <hi>great</hi> ignorance of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> that at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Reformation many of them knew ſo little of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> as-to believe that it was a Book which had been written by <hi>Luther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe they ſet up unwritten Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of which it may be ſome are true, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51305:15"/>ſome are fabulous, and make them all of equal Authority with the <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe they make the Authority of the Scriptures ſo dependant upon their <hi>own</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that without it, they are of no more Authority than <hi>Eſops Fables,</hi> as ſome of them have ſaid, and others of them <hi>commend</hi> the ſaying.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe though they hold the Foundation, they have built upon that Foundation ſuch things as St.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> calleth <hi>Wood, Hay</hi> and <hi>Stubble,</hi> and would make the World believe that they are <hi>Gold, Silver, Precious Stones;</hi> which is not the part of a Pillar and Ground of Truth.</p>
            <p>But, Thirdly, The <hi>Pillar</hi> and <hi>Ground</hi> of Truth as it is in the Text, that is a Pillar ſet upon a Baſis or Foundation, which keeps it <hi>firm</hi> and <hi>ſtedfast,</hi> is a very good expreſſion of ſuch a profeſſion of the <hi>Truth</hi> as is without <hi>wavering.</hi> In which ſenſe St. <hi>Baſil</hi> calleth <hi>Abraham</hi> a <hi>Pillar</hi> of Faith, becauſe when he was tempted with a great temptation, <hi>He ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered not through <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief,
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.20.</note> but was ſtrong in the Faith.</hi> And in an Epiſtle written by the Churches of <hi>Vienna</hi> and <hi>Lyons,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Euſebius;</hi> the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> who ſuffer'd a great Perſecution for their Faith, and were not <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:51305:15"/>in it, are called <hi>Pillars;</hi> and <hi>Atalus,</hi> one of great note among them, is called a <hi>Pillar and Ground of the Church.</hi> And in this ſenſe the <hi>Catholick and Apostolick Church may well be called the Pillar and Ground of the Truth; Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mota Columna,</hi> a Pillar that ſtood unmoved upon that Ground on which it was ſet. For though ſome Local Churches, which were but as ſo many <hi>Candleſticks,</hi> though they were of <hi>Gold,</hi> have been removed; the <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> Church was ſo well ſetled upon a <hi>ſure</hi> and <hi>ſtrong</hi> Foundation, that all the means which have been uſed to <hi>overthrow</hi> it, have ſerved to <hi>eſtabliſh</hi> it.</p>
            <p>Great Endeavours were us'd at firſt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the ſetting up of this <hi>Pillar</hi> upon the <hi>Ground</hi> of it, by them whom the Scripture calleth the <hi>Builders:</hi> but the Deſtruction which they thought to bring upon the <hi>Pillar</hi> and the <hi>Ground,</hi> fell upon <hi>themſelves;</hi> and the Deſtruction which fell upon themſelves, ſerv'd very much to the <hi>Edification</hi> of that <hi>Pillar</hi> and <hi>Ground</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> which they ſought to deſtroy.</p>
            <p>No ſooner was the <hi>Pillar</hi> ſet up upon the <hi>Ground,</hi> but great Force and Violence was uſed to throw it down. The <hi>Kings</hi> of the Earth were aſſembled, and the <hi>Princes</hi> took
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51305:16"/>counſel together againſt it, as the <hi>Children of</hi> Edom <hi>in the day of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>Down with it, down with it even to the ground.</hi> But all the Force and Violence which they uſed to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it, ſerv'd to let them ſee that it was ſo well ſetled upon a <hi>ſure</hi> and <hi>ſtrong</hi> Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, that it could not be <hi>overthrown.</hi> And as all the <hi>Pillars</hi> of <hi>Heatheniſh Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Superſtition,</hi> which were ſo many <hi>Pillars of Lyes,</hi> fell before it like <hi>Dagon</hi> before the <hi>Ark of God;</hi> ſo that we may ſay of them as the Angel ſaid of <hi>Babylon,
<note place="margin">Revel. 18.2.</note> Babylon is faln, is faln,</hi> So we may ſay of this <hi>Pillar</hi> and <hi>Ground</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> as Chriſt ſaith of the Houſe built upon a Rock, <hi>The Rain deſcended,
<note place="margin">Matth. 7.25.</note> and the Floods came, and the Winds blew, and beat upon it, and it fell not; for it was founded upon a Rock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There have been from the beginning ſuch as St.
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> calls <hi>Falſe Prophets, who have privily brought in damnable Hereſies, denying the Lord that bought them, and have brought upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſwift deſtruction.</hi> But that ſwift deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which they have brought upon <hi>themſelves,</hi> hath ſerved to the <hi>Edification</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in that <hi>Truth</hi> which they ſought to <hi>deſtroy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this <hi>Pillar and Ground of Truth</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in ſo much danger to be thrown <hi>down</hi> by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51305:16"/>all the force and violence which <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> have rais'd againſt it; nor to be <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined</hi> by all the <hi>Hereſies</hi> which <hi>Falſe Prophets</hi> and <hi>Falſe Apoſtles</hi> have deviſed, as the <hi>Truth</hi> of it hath been to be <hi>perverted</hi> by <hi>that</hi> Church, which hath endeavoured <hi>defendendo concutere,</hi> to ſhake this Pillar and Ground by ſeeming to defend it. For though it hath not removed the Pillar from the <hi>Ground,</hi> but is ſo far <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick,</hi> as to hold the Foundation of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>Other Foundation can no man lay, ſave that which is laid, Jeſus Christ;</hi> they have done great <hi>wrong</hi> to the Truth, by <hi>defacing</hi> the <hi>ancient Inſcriptions</hi> which were firſt written upon this Pillar, with ſuch <hi>Alterations</hi> and <hi>Additions</hi> as they have made. But all theſe <hi>Alterations</hi> and <hi>Additions</hi> have ſerved to raiſe up many <hi>learned</hi> men, and not a few of them of this <hi>Church of England,</hi> to revive thoſe <hi>ancient</hi> Inſcriptions, and make many Truths, which are good and profitable, to be known more <hi>legible</hi> than they were before.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of a time <hi>that ſhould come,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3.</note> when men would not endure ſound Doctrine, but according to their own luſts they would heap up to themſelves Teachers, having itching ears.</hi> But as he ſaith in another place,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.19.</note> 
               <hi>There muſt be Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51305:17"/>that they which are approved may be made manifeſt:</hi> So we may ſay of theſe <hi>itching ears,</hi> and the confuſed multitude of <hi>Teachers,</hi> which they have heaped to <hi>themſelves,</hi> They have ſerv'd to make them that are <hi>approved</hi> for <hi>hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faſt the form of ſound words,</hi> and Doctrine, which they have received from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick Church,</hi> the more <hi>manifeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some Profane Wits have pleas'd themſelves in making <hi>Paſquins,</hi> and clapping them upon this Pillar; but they could never make them ſtick ſo faſt, but that they have faln to the ground, and been trodden under feet of men. But the Pillar and Ground of Truth can never fall: The Ground on which it ſtands is the <hi>Rock,
<note place="margin">Matth. 16.18</note> againſt which the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail:</hi> The <hi>Faith</hi> by which it ſtands is the Belief of a <hi>Kingdom which cannot be moved:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.28.</note> The Doctrine which is built upon this Faith is <hi>Sound Doctrine;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.9.</note> and as there have been, ſo there will be ſo many holding the profeſſion of this Faith and Doctrine <hi>without wavering,</hi> as will keep up this <hi>Pillar</hi> and <hi>Ground</hi> of Truth ſo long as the Pillars of Heaven and Earth ſhall ſtand; and till He who is <hi>the Author and Finiſher of our Faith,</hi> bring us to the end of our Faith, which is the Salvation of our Souls.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
